<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<transcript><text start="16.49" dur="5.49">You know my staff asked me what I wanted for
my birthday. I was thinking maybe it would</text><text start="21.98" dur="4.43">be something like a cake, something traditional.
Instead they said, ‘Let’s do an executive</text><text start="26.41" dur="6.59">budget presentation.’ So you’re getting
to experience it with me.</text><text start="33" dur="6.96">I want to express my appreciation to our OMB
Director Dean Fuleihan and to his extraordinary</text><text start="39.96" dur="7">staff. They have worked intense hours over
these last weeks and months. And we have been</text><text start="46.97" dur="4.159">here burning the midnight oil many a time.
And a thank you to all the members of the</text><text start="51.129" dur="4.71">administration who contributed so much to
the process of arriving at this executive</text><text start="55.839" dur="6.04">budget. It’s been a painstaking process,
but one that I think will be reflected positively</text><text start="61.879" dur="1.551">in the product.</text><text start="63.43" dur="4.41">We are going to go over this. I’ll give
my remarks, Dean will give some remarks. We’ll</text><text start="67.84" dur="3.23">go to questions. Just emphasizing from the
beginning, all questions today will be on</text><text start="71.07" dur="1.71">the topic of the budget.</text><text start="72.78" dur="7">Again, the executive budget for Fiscal 2015
will be $73.9 billion, $73.9 billion. We arrived</text><text start="84.17" dur="5.979">at this budget with really a fantastic partnership
from the City Council, from Speaker Mark-Viverito</text><text start="90.149" dur="5.9">and all of her colleagues, and from working
with elected officials and community leaders</text><text start="96.049" dur="5.191">all over the city as we developed a number
of our initiatives. And we’ll continue to</text><text start="101.24" dur="5.53">have a collaborative process for the remainder
of the budget season, leading up to adoption</text><text start="106.77" dur="7">in June. The City Council, of course, will
start its hearings soon and work with us towards</text><text start="113.96" dur="1.71">adoption.</text><text start="115.67" dur="6.64">Now, let me state something at the outset.
Budgets are not just a collection of numbers.</text><text start="122.31" dur="7">They are not just accounting documents. They
reflect fundamental values. And if you ask</text><text start="130.2" dur="4.09">someone what they fund, you will be able to
see what they actually believe in. I think</text><text start="134.29" dur="4.86">in this budget, you will see clearly what
I believe in, what this administration believes</text><text start="139.15" dur="0.25">in.</text><text start="139.26" dur="6.84">I like to quote some of my heroes, one of
them in particular, Mayor Fiorello LaGuardia.</text><text start="146.1" dur="4.99">He said he had a “golden rule” for his
administration. He said, “Do after the election</text><text start="151.09" dur="3.42">as you said you would do before the election.”</text><text start="154.51" dur="5.66">I think that typifies a lot of what we’ve
tried to do in these months. And it’s something</text><text start="160.17" dur="4.94">we believe in and that has led us to creating
a budget that reflects three core values,</text><text start="165.11" dur="3.55">the same that we talked about at the time
of the preliminary budget – a budget that</text><text start="168.66" dur="4.05">is responsible, progressive and honest.</text><text start="172.71" dur="6.11">Responsible, because we know the first thing
we have to achieve in the budget process is</text><text start="178.82" dur="4.09">to be fiscally prudent, to be smart about
where we stand now and where we need to stand</text><text start="182.91" dur="7">in the future. We, in this budget, are straightforward
about the structural deficits we face going</text><text start="190.97" dur="3.62">forward. We’re straightforward about the
challenges we face, and some of the advantages</text><text start="194.59" dur="6.23">we bring to bear. And we’re sober about
what we need to address and we’ve tried</text><text start="200.82" dur="6.77">to show that approach with our labor contracts,
taking a situation that for years was unresolved</text><text start="207.59" dur="4.82">and actually getting to the kind of resolution
that allows us to plug in specific numbers.</text><text start="212.41" dur="4.79">You’ll see throughout this presentation
a lot of things that were not clear in previous</text><text start="217.2" dur="4.1">years and budgets are suddenly becoming clear,
because for the first time you’re going</text><text start="221.3" dur="1.43">to have real numbers.</text><text start="222.73" dur="5.39">And because of the labor settlement that we’re
in the process of achieving – obviously</text><text start="228.12" dur="4.39">I hasten to add, there are ratification votes
ahead and individual union contracts ahead</text><text start="232.51" dur="5.86">– but because we’ve made this substantial
progress, we’re able now to project a real</text><text start="238.37" dur="5.02">budget – not just a theory, but something
that we believe will hold over the years ahead.</text><text start="243.39" dur="7">I remind you that we inherited 152 unresolved
labor contracts – again, an unprecedented</text><text start="251.25" dur="7">reality in the history of this city. Some
dated as far back as 2008. There had never</text><text start="259.22" dur="6.229">been such a difficult task in terms of labor
relations in the history of this city. There</text><text start="265.449" dur="6.59">had never been such a fiscal uncertainty when
it came to labor as to have all of our contracts</text><text start="272.039" dur="7">open. And I credit again Tony Shorris and
Bob Linn, Dean Fuleihan, Stan Brezenoff, all</text><text start="280.46" dur="4.049">of the individuals – especially Bob Linn,
who put in such an extraordinary effort to</text><text start="284.509" dur="5.731">resolve these contracts and get us out of
that greatness and confusion and into a situation</text><text start="290.24" dur="2.389">where we had some certainty for the future
of this city.</text><text start="292.629" dur="6.301">And the UFT contract, obviously pending ratification
– I’ll note that there was a very – an</text><text start="298.93" dur="6.259">overwhelmingly positive vote in favor the
contract at the UFT delegate assembly, but</text><text start="305.189" dur="6.211">we know there’s a fuller ratification process
ahead. The contract achieved a number of things</text><text start="311.4" dur="7">that had been deemed nearly impossible by
various pundits – obviously resolving a</text><text start="319.24" dur="6.579">host of past issues, making sure that we had
an affordable plan going forward – what</text><text start="325.819" dur="7">will be over the years that were not covered
by the element particular to the years 2008/2009,</text><text start="334.74" dur="5.38">but for the years thereafter, the seven years,
the contract provides 10 percent increases</text><text start="340.12" dur="7">over that seven-year timeframe to finance
with a number of achievements in healthcare</text><text start="349.06" dur="3.409">savings that we’re very, very proud of.</text><text start="352.469" dur="4.341">Again, we’ve talked about the UFT budget.
We’ve also talked about the fact that those</text><text start="356.81" dur="5.12">healthcare savings are extrapolated over all
the municipal contracts – again, pending</text><text start="361.93" dur="5.59">ratification, pending details – that would
amount to $3.4 billion in healthcare savings</text><text start="367.52" dur="4.69">over the term of these contracts. We also
want to clarify, there will be an additional</text><text start="372.21" dur="5.739">billion dollars made available from the Health
Stabilization Fund. This is another step of</text><text start="377.949" dur="7">progress that came from a productive and constructive
relationship between management and labor.</text><text start="385.039" dur="5.201">So that’s $3.4 billion, again, extrapolating
across all the unions, across the whole timeframe</text><text start="390.24" dur="3.87">in healthcare savings, plus an additional
billion dollars that has been freed up from</text><text start="394.11" dur="1.88">the health stabilization fund.</text><text start="395.99" dur="7">I want to emphasize that these savings are
enforceable by arbitration. We are absolutely</text><text start="403.699" dur="7">convinced that the process will guarantee
that these savings are achieved. And this</text><text start="411.18" dur="5.379">labor deal with the UFT is not only fair to
our educators but includes a number of important</text><text start="416.559" dur="6.771">reforms that we think will greatly improve
and modernize our school system.</text><text start="423.33" dur="3.75">We know – I always qualify that there’s
a lot of steps ahead, but we also know in</text><text start="427.08" dur="4.209">the history of New York City labor relations
that the first major agreement has generally</text><text start="431.289" dur="5">set the pattern for later ones. So we believe
that this agreement is a very, very promising</text><text start="436.289" dur="1.41">start.</text><text start="437.699" dur="5.541">Now, at the time of the preliminary budget
that was the number one question mark, whether</text><text start="443.24" dur="5.759">we could get to a labor settlement and when
and how. There were also major question marks</text><text start="448.999" dur="2.85">at that time in February regarding state and
federal aid.</text><text start="451.849" dur="5.93">Well, on the state front, we’re very appreciative
and very proud of the achievements, obviously,</text><text start="457.779" dur="6.91">crucially, the important funding for UPK,
the largest school aid increase in many years</text><text start="464.689" dur="5.421">– and that school aid made flexible so it
could be used in part to achieve some of what</text><text start="470.11" dur="5.419">we need to initially for after-school. So,
where there had been giant question marks</text><text start="475.529" dur="3.801">before, now we have a number of good answers
that came out of the process in Albany.</text><text start="479.33" dur="6.78">And on the federal front, although a number
of question marks remain, one major piece</text><text start="486.11" dur="3.66">of progress that was achieved in recent months
was the Medicaid waiver. That will play a</text><text start="489.77" dur="3.63">fundamental role is securing healthcare for
communities all over the city going forward.</text><text start="493.4" dur="4.109">And I want to particularly thank Governor
Cuomo for his extraordinary efforts to achieve</text><text start="497.509" dur="0.65">that waiver.</text><text start="498.159" dur="6.431">Now, I just want to say at the outset, there
are some – I’ve met them over the years</text><text start="504.59" dur="5.84">– who have trouble equating fiscal responsibility
with progressive values. I think the two must</text><text start="510.43" dur="3.739">go hand in hand. I think part of being an
honest progressive is recognizing the world</text><text start="514.169" dur="7">as it is and achieving the kinds of savings
that allow us to actually do the good work</text><text start="521.669" dur="7">of government consistently. So, there is nothing
unprogressive about being fiscally prudent.</text><text start="529.25" dur="6.99">In fact, it’s necessary. And, if you believe
in the positive role of government as I do,</text><text start="536.24" dur="5.959">then you need a strong and stable foundation
to allow us to take the steps we need to to</text><text start="542.199" dur="5.14">create more fairness in people’s lives.
A government that is wracked by fiscal instability</text><text start="547.339" dur="4.021">simply can’t do that. A government that
has a strong plan going forward is in a position</text><text start="551.36" dur="2.26">to do a lot of good for people.</text><text start="553.62" dur="5.18">Another one of my heroes, President Franklin
Roosevelt, had a very simple point on this</text><text start="558.8" dur="4.24">matter. I’d like to quote it. I think it
says a lot. He said, “Too often liberal</text><text start="563.04" dur="7">governments have been wrecked on the rocks
of lose fiscal policy.” I know that that</text><text start="570.22" dur="6.78">quote warms the hearts of my OMB brothers
and sisters, but it’s true. And so we intend</text><text start="577" dur="5.04">to be both progressive and fiscally prudent
and this document, I think, provides evidence</text><text start="582.04" dur="1.909">that we are on that road.</text><text start="583.949" dur="7">Let’s talk about the city economy. It’s
generally strong and we have really made great</text><text start="591.519" dur="3.75">progress at diversifying our economy. And
I give credit to the previous administration</text><text start="595.269" dur="5.111">for their efforts and we’re going to expand
upon those. But the improvements we’ve experienced</text><text start="600.38" dur="5.329">economically are uneven and, in large measure,
fragile. And we need to be honest about that</text><text start="605.709" dur="2.171">and we need to be cautious about that.</text><text start="607.88" dur="3.579">Obviously the benefits of our economy are
not being shared by a number of our fellow</text><text start="611.459" dur="5.711">citizens, and we certainly cannot be sure
that economic times will remain getting better.</text><text start="617.17" dur="5.58">We have to be ready for the potential that
they might dip down again. Now, if you look</text><text start="622.75" dur="7">at GDP growth, it&amp;#39;s recovered from the negative
growth of the Great Recession, and forecast</text><text start="630.19" dur="6.389">to continue to rise over the next few years,
finally climbing above 3 percent in 2015.</text><text start="636.579" dur="4.711">This will be the first time we&amp;#39;ve seen that
since the beginning of the Great Recession.</text><text start="641.29" dur="6.57">Again, cause for some optimism, but cautious
optimism in our view. Because you can also</text><text start="647.86" dur="7">see how fitful the recovery has been, and
how incomplete. And again, very serious disconnect</text><text start="657.769" dur="5.361">from some of what you see there in that chart
that might cause a sense that things are really</text><text start="663.13" dur="4.889">happening for people across the board versus
the reality we know on the ground that&amp;#39;s much</text><text start="668.019" dur="7">more complex. Our city&amp;#39;s gross product, similarly,
has finally exceeded pre-recession peak levels.</text><text start="676.81" dur="4.42">This is the first time since the beginning
of the recession – and that was in 2013</text><text start="681.23" dur="6.12">– we finally exceeded that level. Again,
a reason for cautious optimism, but it took</text><text start="687.35" dur="4.2">quite a while to get there from a crisis that
began in 2008.</text><text start="691.55" dur="7">Now, our city industries, almost all of them
are up now from their low point of 2009 – some</text><text start="701.19" dur="5.28">only up a little, as you can see. But I want
to emphasize that much of the recovery has</text><text start="706.47" dur="4.45">happened with some of the industries, unfortunately,
that have the lowest paying jobs. I&amp;#39;m going</text><text start="710.92" dur="4.76">to step over here for a second. As you see,
leisure &amp;amp; hospitality in 2012, the average</text><text start="715.68" dur="2.98">wage – $37,000. Retail, average way – $36,000.
Other services, average wage – $44,000.</text><text start="718.66" dur="7">So, some of the areas that are strong also
form the lower-wage, lower-benefit jobs.</text><text start="734.129" dur="5.75">Our message, and it&amp;#39;s clear in this budget,
it&amp;#39;s clear in so much of the work that Deputy</text><text start="739.879" dur="4.721">Mayor Glen is doing, is we have to build our
economy, we have to expand the economy of</text><text start="744.6" dur="5.14">this city, further diversify it, create a
large number of new jobs, while pushing up</text><text start="749.74" dur="6.039">the wage and benefit levels, trying to particularly
intensify those sectors that do a better job</text><text start="755.779" dur="5.271">at providing strong wages and benefits. Those
would obviously include the technology sector,</text><text start="761.05" dur="7">and the film and TV sectors. So, we are focused
on job growth, both quantitatively and qualitatively.</text><text start="769.24" dur="5.459">Because although we appreciate the creation
of any and all jobs, this chart point outs</text><text start="774.699" dur="3.18">that we&amp;#39;ve got to do better on the qualitative
side.</text><text start="777.879" dur="7">And, we&amp;#39;re focused on all the tools we have,
and I remind you that even in our huge affordable</text><text start="785.509" dur="5.13">housing plan, there is a big employment impact
in construction, and in permanent jobs, in</text><text start="790.639" dur="5.711">the work we&amp;#39;re doing to recover from Sandy,
and foster resiliency, there are great opportunities</text><text start="796.35" dur="5.21">for job creation for our residents, and we&amp;#39;re
going to take advantage of each of those opportunities.</text><text start="801.56" dur="7">Looking now at construction levels, and this
is reflected by building permits. Construction</text><text start="808.589" dur="7">levels still well below pre-recession levels
– another indication of progress, but fragility.</text><text start="816.06" dur="3.92">We again believe that as we progress with
our affordable housing plan, you&amp;#39;ll start</text><text start="819.98" dur="5.029">to see some real movement in this number.
And we&amp;#39;re very proud of the fact that this</text><text start="825.009" dur="5.81">plan will give a great boost to this sector.
And I also got unemployment rates, and this</text><text start="830.819" dur="7">is as of January of this year, the city is
still about a point above the national average.</text><text start="837.959" dur="7">The United States now at 6.6 percent in January,
New York City at 7.8 percent. This also shows</text><text start="846.43" dur="5.139">real improvement since the height of the great
recession, but I hasten to add, this is still</text><text start="851.569" dur="5.791">too high an unemployment rate – 7.8 percent
for the city is still higher than it – than</text><text start="857.36" dur="4.74">we want it to be, and then we will allow it
to be, if all of our efforts hopefully have</text><text start="862.1" dur="4.219">the effect that we intend them to.</text><text start="866.319" dur="4.601">And we&amp;#39;ve also seen in the reports that have
just come out recently, from the Bureau of</text><text start="870.92" dur="5.56">Labor Statistics – unemployment rate, unfortunately,
is understating the problem on the ground.</text><text start="876.48" dur="5.729">A lot of workers have been dropping out of
the workforce, so nationally, workforce participation</text><text start="882.209" dur="7">rates are below 63 percent. That is the lowest
in 30 years. So, some progress but also real</text><text start="890.129" dur="4.051">indication of other realities we have to be
sober about.</text><text start="894.18" dur="6.98">Nationally, 783,000 quote-unquote, so-called
“discouraged workers” were indicated last</text><text start="901.16" dur="5.779">month. That’s people who are no longer looking
for work. And there’s a qualitative issue</text><text start="906.939" dur="7">here too. Salaries have been falling. From
2007 to 2012, wages fell for the bottom 70</text><text start="916.31" dur="4.759">percent of workers according to income. So
even as productivity continued to grow, wages</text><text start="921.069" dur="5.87">fell for a very, very large swath of the people
of this city and the country. That’s based</text><text start="926.939" dur="2.94">on a study by the Economic Policy Institute.</text><text start="929.879" dur="6.15">And, we’ve talked about it before, we need
to talk about it again – Income inequality</text><text start="936.029" dur="7">– large problem, a growing problem globally,
nationally. Nationally, income inequality</text><text start="943.399" dur="5.37">is at levels not seen since the 1920s. Here’s
the picture in New York City.</text><text start="948.769" dur="5.841">In the last ten years, the top 1 percent of
earners in this city have taken in a far larger</text><text start="954.61" dur="4.079">percentage of all income, while middle class
and lower income New Yorkers have been in</text><text start="958.689" dur="6.731">a stagnant position. We obviously are focused
on bringing up the wages and benefits of those</text><text start="965.42" dur="5.649">lower income and middle class New Yorkers,
and addressing the expenses in their lives</text><text start="971.069" dur="4.911">with tools like the Affordable Housing Plan,
and using all of the tools we have. Obviously,</text><text start="975.98" dur="4.94">paid-sick leave has an impact on benefit levels.
A host of tools we have to address this phenomenon,</text><text start="980.92" dur="7">and start to arrest it. Looking at the overall
reality of our people, we’ve seen over the</text><text start="989.16" dur="7">last five years this growing trend confirmed
in a report last year by the Bloomberg Administration,</text><text start="996.48" dur="7">just reconfirmed by the same NYC CEO report
– about 46 percent of New Yorkers at or</text><text start="1003.68" dur="6.11">near the poverty level. So we see a reality,
a kind of dual reality where one swath of</text><text start="1009.79" dur="5.2">the city doing ever better, another swath
of the city really in a delicate and fragile</text><text start="1014.99" dur="4.889">position that is not improving, and we have
to address urgently.</text><text start="1019.879" dur="6.861">Now let’s look at where we stand in terms
of this economic recovery. This is a very</text><text start="1026.74" dur="4.579">interesting chart. I did not know – and
since this is my birthday I’ll indicate</text><text start="1031.319" dur="6.041">this – this was one of the greatest recoveries
in history, two months before I was born [Inaudible]</text><text start="1037.36" dur="7">contributed in my own way. [Inaudible] And
here is a lot of the Clinton years, 10 full</text><text start="1045.72" dur="2.55">years recovery. But this is more typically
what an economic recovery looks like. But</text><text start="1048.27" dur="7">right now, right around the midpoint, this
is where we stand today. So, the folks at</text><text start="1058.179" dur="6.811">OMB will tell you we have to be cautious when
you see a recovery that has moved for this</text><text start="1064.99" dur="4.01">long – and thank God has made some progress,
not as much as we would hope, but some progress</text><text start="1069" dur="5.539">– you have to start asking the question:
When does that start to turn? And there are</text><text start="1074.539" dur="4.451">some economists who think that this expansion
may be running out of steam. We are sober</text><text start="1078.99" dur="3.85">about the fact that when recoveries end there’s
not – you don’t get a memo alerting you</text><text start="1082.84" dur="4.28">to the fact. It just starts to happen, and
that’s part of why you’ll see some careful</text><text start="1087.12" dur="4.539">measures in this budget, to guard our fiscal
future.</text><text start="1091.659" dur="6.821">Now we’ll give you an overview of our financial
plan. We’ve been here now just over four</text><text start="1098.48" dur="4.29">months, and in that time we have addressed
a series of very serious fiscal issues and</text><text start="1102.77" dur="4.59">management issues that were ignored for quite
a while that needed to be addressed. You’re</text><text start="1107.36" dur="5.14">going to see these numbers play out over years.
They had to be addressed. They had to be addressed</text><text start="1112.5" dur="5.779">once and for all. We had to get to a point
of fiscal normalcy and normalcy in labor management</text><text start="1118.279" dur="4.831">relations. And we were devoted to the notion
that we could achieve it, and that we could</text><text start="1123.11" dur="4.29">achieve it without a property tax increase.
And I’m proud to say we were able to achieve</text><text start="1127.4" dur="5">these exchanges without a property tax increase.
So therefore the budget – the executive</text><text start="1132.4" dur="4.45">budget – is balanced for the current fiscal
year, Fiscal ’14, and is balanced for next</text><text start="1136.85" dur="2.42">year, Fiscal ’15.</text><text start="1139.27" dur="7">Again, emphasizing the budget estimates reflect
the UFT pattern – the 10 percent increase</text><text start="1147.32" dur="6.93">over seven years, again pending ratifications.
But it really removes what was the greatest</text><text start="1154.25" dur="7">source of uncertainty in this process. The
rating agency Moody’s noted in its analysis</text><text start="1162.19" dur="6.4">of the labor deal that, if approved, it would
mean, “Resolution of a longstanding budgetary</text><text start="1168.59" dur="6.67">risk for the city.” It’s the simplest
way to put it from one of the entities that</text><text start="1175.26" dur="4.94">watches our finances closely. This resolves
something that was outstanding, that was creating</text><text start="1180.2" dur="5.829">a deep uncertainty. We’re proud to now be
moving in the right direction.</text><text start="1186.029" dur="4.591">This budget realistically acknowledges the
risks we face. So I’ve talked about the</text><text start="1190.62" dur="5.45">federal funding dynamics. There will likely
be additional cuts because of the sequestration.</text><text start="1196.07" dur="5.88">And that will reduce federal funds. We all
know that sadly a number of the areas of federal</text><text start="1201.95" dur="5.579">spending that are targeted by the sequestration
hit New York City very hard. We clearly are</text><text start="1207.529" dur="4.671">engaged in ongoing conversations with the
federal administration on Sandy relief, and</text><text start="1212.2" dur="7">those issues are unresolved. We know for a
fact that not only are recoveries – economic</text><text start="1219.99" dur="6.34">recoveries – uncertain, we know that tax
revenue is – by definition – always uncertain.</text><text start="1226.33" dur="6.24">And we saw in our neighboring states some
recent actions that indicated this, particularly</text><text start="1232.57" dur="6.829">in the case of New Jersey which now has an
$800 million budget deficit because the state</text><text start="1239.399" dur="4.88">had been too generous in their assumptions
about personal income tax revenue. We are</text><text start="1244.279" dur="5.861">being careful in our assumptions because we
want to stay ahead of the situation.</text><text start="1250.14" dur="7">Now, looking ahead, we continue to face multi-billion
dollar budget gaps in the out years. This</text><text start="1258.299" dur="6.411">is the structural deficit that we know we
still face. The good news is these are manageable</text><text start="1264.71" dur="3.81">deficits. We’re confident that we will be
able to handle them in time and they’re</text><text start="1268.52" dur="7">well below the deficits that we’ve seen
in the last decade or so. Let me indicate</text><text start="1275.6" dur="3.929">here, this is Fiscal ’16, just over $2 billion;
Fiscal ’17, just over $2 billion, Fiscal</text><text start="1279.529" dur="7">’18 just over $3 billion. And again, you’ll
see the comparison to the average over the</text><text start="1291.6" dur="6.25">previous 12 years. The average for what would
be the third year of the budget, $3 billion,</text><text start="1297.85" dur="5.829">$3.7 billion. So in comparison, we feel that
we’re in a strong position, but we know</text><text start="1303.679" dur="3.451">we have real work to do to close those deficits
going forward.</text><text start="1307.13" dur="7">As I said, the focus of a lot of what we do
is to strengthen the city’s economy – in</text><text start="1314.64" dur="3.71">general, to increase the number of jobs and
economic activity to make sure that wages</text><text start="1318.35" dur="6.809">and benefits go up to address the issues of
income inequality and poverty. All of the</text><text start="1325.159" dur="5.171">pieces fit. The signature program of pre-K
and after-school does a lot for our children</text><text start="1330.33" dur="3.9">in terms of their future economically. It
does a lot for parents right now in terms</text><text start="1334.23" dur="3.5">of providing services they need, that for
many parents come out of their pocket when</text><text start="1337.73" dur="4.63">it comes to pre-K and after-school. That won’t
be the case going forward for so many parents.</text><text start="1342.36" dur="5.78">It gives a lot of hardworking people, a lot
of single parents in particular an opportunity</text><text start="1348.14" dur="4.99">to work and have flexibility so they can do
better economically.</text><text start="1353.13" dur="6.88">And the investments that we’re making in
CUNY in particular focus on getting jobs for</text><text start="1360.01" dur="6.73">New Yorkers now. We’re investing $20 million
in STEM education, in two-year colleges and</text><text start="1366.74" dur="5.35">community colleges at CUNY to provide a real
and immediate opportunity for New Yorkers</text><text start="1372.09" dur="3.73">to get the kind of training they need to go
right into the tech industry – and that</text><text start="1375.82" dur="3.45">is not only important in terms of getting
our people to jobs, but these, again, are</text><text start="1379.27" dur="4.6">often quality, good-paying jobs. And one of
the things I’m most excited about in this</text><text start="1383.87" dur="4.929">budget is that focus on CUNY and that focus
on credentialing more New Yorkers to participate</text><text start="1388.799" dur="2.191">in the growth of the tech industry.</text><text start="1390.99" dur="7">The affordable housing plan – on every level
– what it will do for families in this city,</text><text start="1398.08" dur="4.319">in terms of the bottom line of their personal
economics making the number one expense in</text><text start="1402.399" dur="6.53">their life more affordable, the jobs it will
create. Again, 200,000 is enough to house</text><text start="1408.929" dur="2.201">almost half a million New Yorkers.</text><text start="1411.13" dur="5.85">Paid sick leave as I mentioned, again, reaching
over half a million more people now, providing</text><text start="1416.98" dur="3.4">a little more economic stability and relief.</text><text start="1420.38" dur="5.88">And the infrastructure work we do also is
crucial for a thriving economy. The infrastructure</text><text start="1426.26" dur="3.549">efforts will create jobs in and of themselves.
And we’re going to make special efforts</text><text start="1429.809" dur="4.321">to make sure those jobs go to New York City
residents as often as possible and folks who</text><text start="1434.13" dur="4.38">have been left out of the economy. But we
also know – and we see it all over the country</text><text start="1438.51" dur="3.639">– if you don’t attend to your infrastructure
needs, your economy cannot continue to grow.</text><text start="1442.149" dur="5.491">So you see a major investment in infrastructure
in this budget.</text><text start="1447.64" dur="4.57">Now, I hasten to add, you’re going to see
a capital plan – a four-year capital plan</text><text start="1452.21" dur="5.23">here. This is the template we’re working
with now. It is also the beginning of a process</text><text start="1457.44" dur="5.55">over the coming months that will lead to January
of next year, when we will be providing a</text><text start="1462.99" dur="6.049">unified, ten-year capital plan. That will
be a forward-looking approach that will really</text><text start="1469.039" dur="4.811">give us the long-term imprint for capital
spending in this city. And so that’s going</text><text start="1473.85" dur="5.679">to be an intensive process over the coming
months. OMB is working with all of our city</text><text start="1479.529" dur="7">agencies, but we start now with this four-year
plan, which indicates a number of our investments.</text><text start="1488.409" dur="6.731">This is a fundamentally progressive budget.
There’s investment in our children, in improved</text><text start="1495.14" dur="3.98">economic opportunity, in affordable housing,
in protection of the most vulnerable, and</text><text start="1499.12" dur="2.539">in increasing public safety for all New Yorkers.</text><text start="1501.659" dur="6.311">Let’s talk about our children first. This
budget, in every way, makes our children a</text><text start="1507.97" dur="5.86">priority. It does so through pre-K and after-school.
It does through the investments we make in</text><text start="1513.83" dur="7">reducing overcrowding, getting our kids of
trailers. And we do all this because we recognize</text><text start="1521.409" dur="3.88">that the current reality in our school system
is unacceptable and it’s not working for</text><text start="1525.289" dur="7">so many of our kids. Again, one in four of
our New York City students who graduated in</text><text start="1532.32" dur="6.709">2013 were college-ready. Three-quarters of
those who graduated were college-ready. Remember,</text><text start="1539.029" dur="4.661">only two-thirds of our kids graduate on time
to begin with. So we know we have to make</text><text start="1543.69" dur="4.719">a series of fundamental changes. You see it
in the capital plan, you see it in pre-K and</text><text start="1548.409" dur="6.101">after-school. You see it in the labor agreement,
in areas like the efforts to retain quality</text><text start="1554.51" dur="6.769">teachers, efforts to focus our strongest teachers
to areas of greatest need – a host of changes</text><text start="1561.279" dur="3.841">that are evident in both the budget and the
labor contract to get at fundamental change</text><text start="1565.12" dur="3.01">in our schools.</text><text start="1568.13" dur="4.679">And the pre-K initiative really undergirds
so much of this, because it is literally the</text><text start="1572.809" dur="5.37">foundation. Someone said to me, after all
the months and months I&amp;#39;ve talked about pre-K,</text><text start="1578.179" dur="2.551">someone said to me offhand the other day,
‘It&amp;#39;s like when you build a house and you</text><text start="1580.73" dur="3.949">have to put down the foundation first.’
And I said, ‘Aha!’ That is the best way</text><text start="1584.679" dur="3.921">to explain it. It is the foundation that makes
everything else possible in education, when</text><text start="1588.6" dur="6.78">it&amp;#39;s done right. And we are moving ahead intensely
with that investment – high quality, full-day</text><text start="1595.38" dur="5.149">pre-K. Now again, the goal for this year – 53,000
seats by September, moving up the following</text><text start="1600.529" dur="6.481">year to 73,000. We made sure we had the space,
the teachers, all the pieces, and that program</text><text start="1607.01" dur="5.73">is moving aggressively. After-school – a
crucial part of what we&amp;#39;re doing – I&amp;#39;ve</text><text start="1612.74" dur="4.029">testified before to you about what it means,
I&amp;#39;ve seen with my own eyes so many times the</text><text start="1616.769" dur="5.171">transcendent impact that after-school can
have – extended learning, homework help,</text><text start="1621.94" dur="5.57">tutoring. Also, our law enforcement officials
will be the first to say that quality after-school</text><text start="1627.51" dur="5.029">programs are intensely helpful to the police,
and other law enforcement professionals, in</text><text start="1632.539" dur="4.961">helping give kids a positive option.</text><text start="1637.5" dur="7">In Fiscal &amp;#39;15, we will reach nearly 100,000
young people with after-school programs at</text><text start="1644.659" dur="7">the middle school level. That’s a substantial
increase – over 30,000 more seats. We&amp;#39;re</text><text start="1651.74" dur="4.83">also going to be doubling the amount of summer
after-school available to over 33,000 seats.</text><text start="1656.57" dur="5.65">As I mentioned, we&amp;#39;re going to make a number
of other investments through our capital plan</text><text start="1662.22" dur="4.22">in education. We&amp;#39;re going to reduce the use
of trailers, which has been a concern to so</text><text start="1666.44" dur="5.82">many parents and teachers. We are going to
reduce overcrowding in a number of areas that</text><text start="1672.26" dur="3.72">have been particularly afflicted – Central
Queens, Lower Manhattan, North Shore of Staten</text><text start="1675.98" dur="3.59">Island, and many others.</text><text start="1679.57" dur="6.569">And we&amp;#39;re going to focus on an area that&amp;#39;s
deserved attention for a long time, arts education.</text><text start="1686.139" dur="6.621">I hasten to say, a lot of our colleagues,
elected officials, notably Comptroller Stringer,</text><text start="1692.76" dur="3.96">a number of community leaders, have really
pushed this point. It&amp;#39;s the right thing to</text><text start="1696.72" dur="4.73">do, but more importantly it&amp;#39;s the state law.
We&amp;#39;re taking major steps towards coming into</text><text start="1701.45" dur="5.79">conformance with that law, and increasing
arts education across our school system. And</text><text start="1707.24" dur="6.09">again, I&amp;#39;ve described the $20 million we&amp;#39;re
putting into the STEM program at CUNY for</text><text start="1713.33" dur="5.43">the community colleges – $20 million in
Fiscal &amp;#39;15 that will reach 5,000 students.</text><text start="1718.76" dur="4.799">That number grows to $50 million a year in
the out years.</text><text start="1723.559" dur="6.85">Now, underlying this budget is a focus on
creating more economic opportunity, and that</text><text start="1730.409" dur="7">takes many forms. One of them is in the area
of small business. A number of you know that</text><text start="1737.58" dur="4.069">I, for years, including in my time as Public
Advocate, pushed for a change in our small</text><text start="1741.649" dur="5.341">business policies. I thought the punitive,
arbitrary approach to fines, the revenue-focused</text><text start="1746.99" dur="4.069">approach, was really undermining small business
and the ability of small business to create</text><text start="1751.059" dur="5.431">jobs. We are making big changes – let me
indicate here.</text><text start="1756.49" dur="0.77">Overall fines [inaudible] Fiscal 2012 – you
go back and look at some of our public advocate</text><text start="1757.26" dur="0.81">reports, we really zeroed in on that year.
That&amp;#39;s when after four or five years of fines</text><text start="1758.07" dur="3.44">at their peak, it’s $859 million a year
across the set of agencies. We want to go</text><text start="1761.51" dur="6.379">down next year to $789 million across those
agencies – that&amp;#39;s an 8 percent overall decrease.</text><text start="1767.889" dur="6.38">But what&amp;#39;s really powerful to look at – these
two agencies, Department of Health and Consumer</text><text start="1774.269" dur="5.961">Affairs were, for many small businesses owners,
really the focal point, where they saw the</text><text start="1780.23" dur="7">most new fines, the most arbitrary fines.
Major increases, looking ahead to Fiscal &amp;#39;15,</text><text start="1791.69" dur="7">over that three year period, you&amp;#39;ll see a
44 percent decrease in Health Department fines</text><text start="1800.65" dur="7">– 44 percent decrease in Health Department
fines, 21 percent decrease in Consumer Affairs</text><text start="1812.309" dur="0.901">fines.</text><text start="1813.21" dur="5.63">And, this is about stabilizing small business
and helping small business to create more</text><text start="1818.84" dur="6.819">jobs. As I said, so much of what we&amp;#39;re doing
has a job creation element – affordable</text><text start="1825.659" dur="4.4">housing plan has a job creation element, Sandy
relief and resiliency has a job creation element</text><text start="1830.059" dur="5.511">– all these pieces come together. The paid
sick leave law, we are convinced, is actually</text><text start="1835.57" dur="5.699">going to strengthen our small businesses by
creating a healthier workforce, more productivity,</text><text start="1841.269" dur="5.311">more consistency in employment, and longevity
in employment, and we&amp;#39;re going to be working</text><text start="1846.58" dur="4.51">closely with small business to make sure that
law is implemented fairly with a strong education</text><text start="1851.09" dur="0.63">effort.</text><text start="1851.72" dur="5.91">We’re also investing in some really wonderful
job creation engines. The Brooklyn Army Terminal</text><text start="1857.63" dur="5.69">is going to get a major new investment over
the next few years that will create more than</text><text start="1863.32" dur="4.9">600 construction jobs and 1,800 permanent
jobs. It will also continue to invest in what’s</text><text start="1868.22" dur="4.65">been one of the great success stories of this
city, the Brooklyn Navy Yard. And this will</text><text start="1872.87" dur="7">all allow us to continue the efforts to diversify
the city economy, including a focus on sophisticated</text><text start="1880.399" dur="5.351">manufacturing that really has shown great
ability to thrive in the city, including areas</text><text start="1885.75" dur="4.13">such as 3-D printing.</text><text start="1889.88" dur="4.6">Sandy relief is on the minds of so many New
Yorkers for good reason. So many people are</text><text start="1894.48" dur="5.049">still waiting for what they deserve. This
budget makes a very consistent and serious</text><text start="1899.529" dur="7">commitment to resolving the needs of the victims
of Sandy. We announced last month an overhaul</text><text start="1906.889" dur="5.02">of our programs, a change and streamlining
of the Build it Back approach. We moved $100</text><text start="1911.909" dur="4.661">million of federal aid over to Build it Back
to strengthen its efforts. We’ve moved a</text><text start="1916.57" dur="4.469">lot of staff out into the boroughs, into Staten
Island and Brooklyn and Queens. We’ve added</text><text start="1921.039" dur="4.86">more buildings inspectors specifically devoted
to working on properties affected by Sandy.</text><text start="1925.899" dur="5.171">We’ve cut back on bureaucracy. We’ve made
a commitment to rebuild 500 homes – I’m</text><text start="1931.07" dur="5.599">sorry, to start to rebuild 500 homes and to
get reimbursement checks out to 500 additional</text><text start="1936.669" dur="4.09">homeowners by the end of the summer. That
process has started intensely.</text><text start="1940.759" dur="4.321">We’re also trying to expand – and we will
expand – financial relief for a number of</text><text start="1945.08" dur="5.24">the victims, making them not have to pay for
water bills that they were charged, even though</text><text start="1950.32" dur="4.839">their houses were destroyed. Making them not
have to pay for additional property tax increases</text><text start="1955.159" dur="5.12">because their homes were finally fixed. Making
sure that they get rental assistance, making</text><text start="1960.279" dur="4.711">sure they get relief from city fees while
they’re in the building back process. So</text><text start="1964.99" dur="6.809">a number of pieces that will come together
to really improve what people are experiencing</text><text start="1971.799" dur="4.681">and getting them back on their feet. Again,
in that process, in that reconstruction process,</text><text start="1976.48" dur="3.74">there will be a substantial number of jobs.
We’re trying, to the maximum extent possible,</text><text start="1980.22" dur="7">to get those jobs to people who were affected
by Sandy to maximize the impact of this funding.</text><text start="1988.029" dur="3.76">You know what we’re doing on affordable
housing, 200,000 units will be enough for</text><text start="1991.789" dur="4.5">500,000 people. I like to quote this. I like
to say this to inspire Alicia Glen – more</text><text start="1996.289" dur="3.87">than the population of Kansas City, more than
the population of Miami, more than the population</text><text start="2000.159" dur="6.73">of Atlanta. Excellent, you’re inspired.
In the process, 194,000 construction jobs,</text><text start="2006.889" dur="7">over 7,000 permanent jobs. The largest affordable
housing plan in the history of New York City</text><text start="2014.2" dur="5.88">and the fastest, undoubtedly. And one that
will really help people to address their fundamental</text><text start="2020.08" dur="2.13">needs and address their largest expense in
their life.</text><text start="2022.21" dur="4.929">But that’s not enough. We have to go at
the loss we’ve been experiencing of affordable</text><text start="2027.139" dur="5.211">housing and rent-regulated housing, so we’re
intensely beefing up HPD’s enforcement capacity.</text><text start="2032.35" dur="7">There will be a number more inspectors and
code enforcement personnel to help go at those</text><text start="2041.19" dur="3.52">landlords who are not doing the right thing,
and those landlords who might be harassing</text><text start="2044.71" dur="6.179">tenants and trying to move them out so they
can get their buildings into a more lucrative</text><text start="2050.889" dur="4.921">situation outside of rent control. We’re
going to fight very hard to make everyone</text><text start="2055.81" dur="1.94">abide by the law.</text><text start="2057.75" dur="5.05">We’re also very proud – I think this is
something that everyone in the administration</text><text start="2062.8" dur="4.95">was particularly devoted to – we are once
again ensuring that NYCHA does not have to</text><text start="2067.75" dur="5.149">pay for its policing services. So the $70
million – a full year’s worth of policing</text><text start="2072.899" dur="4.27">services – we paid for through this budget,
not out of NYCHA’s coffers. So that $70</text><text start="2077.169" dur="6.831">million will go back to NYCHA for continued
efforts at repairs and security.</text><text start="2084" dur="7">We’re focused on a number of our fellow
citizens who are most vulnerable. That includes</text><text start="2092.55" dur="4.96">folks who don’t have a roof over their head,
folks who end up in shelter. We are adamant</text><text start="2097.51" dur="5.17">that we must reduce the number of people in
shelter and get them good solutions. We also</text><text start="2102.68" dur="7">want to keep people who are in housing from
slipping into shelter. We fully fund the 30</text><text start="2110.9" dur="5.4">percent rent cap for HIV and AIDS patients.
We have a variety of tools we’re going to</text><text start="2116.3" dur="4.799">use to help people from becoming homeless
– anti-eviction and legal services and rent</text><text start="2121.099" dur="5.321">subsidizies. We have a variety of tools including
those, and our new affordable housing plan,</text><text start="2126.42" dur="5.13">including the supportive housing element of
it, and selective use of Section 8 vouchers</text><text start="2131.55" dur="4.89">and NYCHA units to help reduce the number
of people in shelter. We’re going to bring</text><text start="2136.44" dur="5.27">all of those tools to bear to start to turn
the tide.</text><text start="2141.71" dur="7">We’re, as always, focused on protecting
our children. I want to thank Deputy Mayor</text><text start="2150.03" dur="5.299">Lilliam Barrios-Paoli for leading the initiative
with ACS. I want to thank Deputy Mayor Richard</text><text start="2155.329" dur="6.621">Buery for leading our Children’s Cabinet.
These two leaders are very focused on changing</text><text start="2161.95" dur="6.86">the way we do things and ensuring that our
children are protected more effectively and</text><text start="2168.81" dur="3.24">that the city is aggressive in those efforts.</text><text start="2172.05" dur="5.529">We also are trying to protect children who
do end up in shelter situations. And that’s</text><text start="2177.579" dur="6.091">why I’m proud to say that the Auburn shelter
that, unfortunately, got so much attention</text><text start="2183.67" dur="5.179">because of what was wrong about it, that there
are no longer any children in that shelter.</text><text start="2188.849" dur="4.371">Due to an intensive effort by the city, all
children have been moved to more appropriate</text><text start="2193.22" dur="4.81">locations. We’re well under way doing the
same with the Catherine Street shelter.</text><text start="2198.03" dur="4.51">And something else that matters to a lot of
us are runaway and homeless youth – in many</text><text start="2202.54" dur="6.18">cases, kids literally pushed out by their
own families, including a number of LGBT youth.</text><text start="2208.72" dur="6.16">We have now 100 new beds for them in our shelter
system, particularly devoted to the needs</text><text start="2214.88" dur="4.25">of those young people. And we want them to
know that whatever they have experienced in</text><text start="2219.13" dur="4.29">their lives, that the City of New York will
protect them.</text><text start="2223.42" dur="6.1">You’ll also see a number of investments
in the kinds of programs that will help to</text><text start="2229.52" dur="5.69">reduce health disparities in our city and
do a lot more in the way of community outreach</text><text start="2235.21" dur="3.149">to proactively address health concerns.</text><text start="2238.359" dur="7">Finally, we are adamant about continuing the
wonderful trend over these last 20 years of</text><text start="2245.78" dur="6.74">a safer city. We’re continuing to keep crime
low and make New York City safer in many ways.</text><text start="2252.52" dur="5.819">And it’s, again, not just about the extraordinary
crime-fighting efforts of the NYPD – which</text><text start="2258.339" dur="3.091">we’re supporting in a number of ways in
this budget – it’s also about the reality</text><text start="2261.43" dur="4.899">of traffic fatalities. It’s an issue I’ve
cared about for a long time, but it really</text><text start="2266.329" dur="7">hit home for me when I saw the 2013 statistics.
In a year when we had 333 homicides – a</text><text start="2274.41" dur="7">record year of great progress – still a
long way to go of course, but a number that</text><text start="2281.43" dur="5.74">many years ago would’ve seemed impossible
to reach – but in that same year of 333</text><text start="2287.17" dur="5.409">homicides, 286 New Yorkers were killed in
traffic accidents. And that really put a point</text><text start="2292.579" dur="6.801">on the fact that addressing these crashes
is an incredibly fundamental part of keeping</text><text start="2299.38" dur="3.84">this city safe, particularly for our children.</text><text start="2303.22" dur="4.5">The Vision Zero plan is being implemented
intensely as we speak. It is already having</text><text start="2307.72" dur="5.06">a very positive effect. You’ll be seeing
more red-light cameras ahead, continued efforts</text><text start="2312.78" dur="7">to lower speed limits, more speed humps and
redesigns of streets, more NYPD enforcement.</text><text start="2322.38" dur="3.939">All of this is already having an effect. You’re
going to see a lot more in Fiscal ’15 because</text><text start="2326.319" dur="2.641">of this budget.</text><text start="2328.96" dur="5.629">And making our streets better is part of our
plan too. We’re adding $49 million in capital</text><text start="2334.589" dur="7">funding for Fiscal ’15 for a total of $226
million for road resurfacing, for repaving.</text><text start="2342.4" dur="7">This will allow us, in Fiscal ’15 to resurface
1,000 lane miles of roads in this city. Something</text><text start="2351.25" dur="3.94">I’ve focused on a lot – our quality of
our bridges – we’re adding an additional</text><text start="2355.19" dur="7">$346 million for bridge rehab to make sure
our bridges are safe for the future.</text><text start="2362.24" dur="4.879">We also recognize that the men and women of
the NYPD who keep us safe have often had to</text><text start="2367.119" dur="5.111">struggle with insufficient facilities, so
we’re making a major investment in upgrading</text><text start="2372.23" dur="5.51">police facilities. There will be a rehab of
the 13 Precinct in Manhattan and the Brooklyn</text><text start="2377.74" dur="7">Narcotics Precinct. There will also be construction
of a new precinct house in the South Bronx</text><text start="2387.119" dur="5.341">in the 40 Precinct – that’s a police precinct
building that’s almost 100 years old. It</text><text start="2392.46" dur="4.08">deserves – the police officers there and
the community deserve better, so we’re going</text><text start="2396.54" dur="6.88">to be building a brand new facility for the
40 Precinct.</text><text start="2403.42" dur="7">And our devotion to an honest budget, by definition,
means moving away more and more from the “budget</text><text start="2411.069" dur="4.25">dance”. I lived it for eight years as a
council member. It didn’t make sense to</text><text start="2415.319" dur="4.26">a lot of us. It didn’t make sense to a lot
of the hard-working folks in non-profits who</text><text start="2419.579" dur="4.23">were trying to provide a service and never
knew what the budget would yield for them</text><text start="2423.809" dur="5.591">and their organizations. We’ve been working
with the council intensely to develop a set</text><text start="2429.4" dur="5.84">of shared goals. And instead of going through
a dance and a Kabuki theater, actually determined</text><text start="2435.24" dur="3.02">together some of the things that had to be
in this budget.</text><text start="2438.26" dur="4.93">We believe this is more fair and honest to
the people of this city. You’re going to</text><text start="2443.19" dur="5.659">see a major investment in the continuity of
the community services that the council funded.</text><text start="2448.849" dur="4.861">That was projected in the preliminary budget
– because it was in the November plan – we’re</text><text start="2453.71" dur="3.859">continuing that. So, a major investment to
continue the community-based services – areas</text><text start="2457.569" dur="4.911">like childcare and senior services that the
council has funded.</text><text start="2462.48" dur="5.52">We’re also trying to be honest about the
real cost of some of the things that we face</text><text start="2468" dur="5.72">in this city. One topic – a sensitive topic
– is the question of snow. Snow cost us</text><text start="2473.72" dur="5.58">– I like this snow-scape – it’s bringing
me back – I’m having flashbacks. We were</text><text start="2479.3" dur="5.17">hit with one of the worst snow years in the
history of New York City. It cost us a lot.</text><text start="2484.47" dur="5.17">We had to make several changes in this budget
to accommodate that. And we’ve added to</text><text start="2489.64" dur="4.969">the 2015 budget in anticipation. Look, you
never know what each year is going to bring.</text><text start="2494.609" dur="4.671">This last winter was extraordinary. I’m
knocking on wood and saying, ‘God forbid</text><text start="2499.28" dur="4.71">we have another one in a row.’ But we know
we have to be ready for more, so we’ve added</text><text start="2503.99" dur="7">to the ’15 budget to be more realistic about
what we might face.</text><text start="2512.39" dur="4.11">Coming down to the end here, and then I’m
going to call up Dean Fuleihan for a few comments</text><text start="2516.5" dur="7">before we open up to questions. The capital
plan – again, we’re trying to be realistic,</text><text start="2525.089" dur="4.47">both about how the plan conforms to our values
and our priorities – I can say them clearly,</text><text start="2529.559" dur="5.491">our priorities in the capital plan are education,
affordable housing, and infrastructure in</text><text start="2535.05" dur="4.279">terms of DOT, roads and bridges.</text><text start="2539.329" dur="6.681">We’re also trying to be clear about how
much time it takes to spend the money effectively.</text><text start="2546.01" dur="3.72">In previous capital plans, we’ve seen some
very unrealistic projections that really made</text><text start="2549.73" dur="4.609">it impossible to honestly track what was going
to happen – money that was booked for things</text><text start="2554.339" dur="3.851">that literally couldn’t happen in one year
or two years or three years. You’ll see</text><text start="2558.19" dur="3.85">in this plan a very different look from what
you saw in the November plan of the previous</text><text start="2562.04" dur="5.24">administration – a spreading-out of the
capital expenditures in a way that we think</text><text start="2567.28" dur="3.48">conforms to the actual reality of getting
things done on the ground.</text><text start="2570.76" dur="6.53">You’ll see those priorities – education,
affordable housing, and infrastructure – reflected.</text><text start="2577.29" dur="7">Total capital commitment for the four years
Fiscal ’14 through Fiscal ’18 is $48.9</text><text start="2584.73" dur="7">billion. The capital plan is $48.9 billion.
And I want to emphasize – another one of</text><text start="2593.41" dur="5.83">my favorite charts – so everyone knows that
when you engage in capital spending, which</text><text start="2599.24" dur="5.04">is absolutely necessary for the present and
future reality of this city, the area you</text><text start="2604.28" dur="3.029">have to be concerned about is what it means
for the debt-service coming out of your expense</text><text start="2607.309" dur="6.841">budget. We were adamant that this debt-service
had to be kept within historic limits. I’m</text><text start="2614.15" dur="3.3">going to point over here on the chart, but
I would say for Fiscal ’15, that number</text><text start="2617.45" dur="7">will be 13.7 percent, which again, is well
within limits.</text><text start="2635.559" dur="7">[Inaudible]</text><text start="2648.72" dur="4.139">And I think I’ll just conclude before I
give you a few scintillating words in Spanish</text><text start="2652.859" dur="6.321">that the bottom line on this plan is that
we were realistic throughout. We were looking</text><text start="2659.18" dur="3.659">not only to what we need to do in the next
year, but what we need to do in the future.</text><text start="2662.839" dur="3.581">We knew those capital investments mattered,
but we knew we had to make them in a prudent</text><text start="2666.42" dur="2.73">way, in an honest way, and we’ve endeavored
to do that.</text><text start="2669.15" dur="0.86">En español.</text><text start="2670.01" dur="5.549">El pre-supuésto de la ciudád que estámos
presentándo hóy otórga más dinéro para</text><text start="2675.559" dur="5.121">escuélas, pára viviénda asequíble y pára
ótros prográmas que mejorarán la vída</text><text start="2680.68" dur="1.28">de los neoyorquínos.</text><text start="2681.96" dur="7">Estámos presentándo un pre-supuésto que
es le-ál a mis valóres y a los valóres</text><text start="2697.589" dur="7">de mi administración. Es un pre-supuésto
responsáble, progresísta, y honésto.</text><text start="2706.319" dur="7">Los pre-supuéstos municipáles fí-jan prioridádes.
Nuéstras prioridádes son: creár una Nueva</text><text start="2715.39" dur="7">York más asequíble, más inclusíva pára
tódas las persónas, y creár empléos, sin</text><text start="2726.77" dur="4.38">dejár de ser fiscal-mente responsábles.</text><text start="2731.15" dur="4.06">Dean Fuleihan will present his presentation
entirely in Spanish, with a brief English</text><text start="2735.21" dur="5.859">translation at the end. I just wanted to see
how agile you were, Dean.</text><text start="2741.069" dur="7">Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I think I&amp;#39;ll save the
Spanish translation for next year. I&amp;#39;m going</text><text start="2752.38" dur="5.77">to briefly go through some of the financial
plan slides for you. The mayor has actually</text><text start="2758.15" dur="6.179">outlined the priorities of this budget, and
outlined the choices and the decisions that</text><text start="2764.329" dur="5.821">were made, that really are reflected in the
numbers. On this, you see the city funds,</text><text start="2770.15" dur="7">revenues, and expenses – city funds in this
case, for the upcoming year, for 2015 – 56.1.</text><text start="2778.17" dur="7">The all funds number that the mayor talked
about was the $73.9 billion for 2015. It shows</text><text start="2789.849" dur="7">that in – as the mayor pointed out – in
2014 and 2015, we are – we are in balance.</text><text start="2797.26" dur="7">And then the out-year gaps – and – so,
the next one, is the city funds and expenses,</text><text start="2812.71" dur="4.56">changes in the financial plan since the preliminary
budget. So…</text><text start="2817.27" dur="0.69">Louder.</text><text start="2817.96" dur="2.09">Yep. I apologize.</text><text start="2820.05" dur="1.39">Project, Dean.</text><text start="2821.44" dur="1.389">My apologies.</text><text start="2822.829" dur="5.561">You took the coward&amp;#39;s way out, Dean. [Inaudible]</text><text start="2828.39" dur="0.699">[Laughter]</text><text start="2829.089" dur="7">This wasn&amp;#39;t part of the – of what we had
gone through. So, the city fund changes for</text><text start="2837.15" dur="7">the 2014-2018 since the February plan – I&amp;#39;ll
just highlight a few. You can see the recognition</text><text start="2846.309" dur="7">in 2014 of a significant increase in revenues.
As the mayor pointed out, while we were cautious</text><text start="2854.16" dur="5.36">in our estimates, and personal income tax
revenues were higher than we expected, they</text><text start="2859.52" dur="4.96">were actually in all of our surrounding – in
the surrounding municipalities – they had</text><text start="2864.48" dur="7">actually over-forecasted and were seeing significant
financial plan problems. I&amp;#39;ll also point out</text><text start="2871.89" dur="7">that our – while our revenue growth is moderate,
it&amp;#39;s still – our personal income tax growth</text><text start="2880.329" dur="7">is higher, actually, than the growth in personal
income. So, it&amp;#39;s thoughtful here to be cautious,</text><text start="2888.88" dur="5.61">and it&amp;#39;s also consistent with where we are
in the recovery. And the mayor showed that</text><text start="2894.49" dur="3.79">slide, that we&amp;#39;re basically in the midpoint,
and of course, this is about the next four</text><text start="2898.28" dur="7">years. It also, at the bottom, has the net
cost of the labor settlement, at the – right</text><text start="2906.15" dur="2.88">above the bold.</text><text start="2909.03" dur="7">The next slide – our controllable agency
expenses, and non-controllable agency expenses.</text><text start="2917.77" dur="5.69">I&amp;#39;m sorry, I went too fast. Controllable agency
expenses – this has been a longstanding</text><text start="2923.46" dur="5.47">tradition in the city to show the different
categories. I&amp;#39;m going to slip over – skip</text><text start="2928.93" dur="4.3">over that, and we&amp;#39;re obviously happy, during
the question and answers, to any questions</text><text start="2933.23" dur="6.78">on this. The next chart, and all these are
in your book, personal service, non-personal</text><text start="2940.01" dur="7">services – in 2014, the current fiscal year,
and then in 2015. The following is actually</text><text start="2948.54" dur="7">just the change on those. And, then we conclude
with the five-year financial plan, which does</text><text start="2957.93" dur="7">have the all-funds number, the $73.9 billion,
at the bottom of that. And with that, I&amp;#39;m</text><text start="2967.94" dur="2.06">done.</text><text start="2970" dur="6.24">You could have done that in Spanish, it was
so brief. All right. Stand with me, Dean.</text><text start="2976.24" dur="7">Okay. Reminding everyone that we will take
questions on the topic of the budget. Let&amp;#39;s</text><text start="2984.099" dur="1.881">go.</text><text start="2985.98" dur="7">[Reporter] One of the things that the City
Council had asked was for more transparency</text><text start="2993.059" dur="2.05">in some of the units of appropriation, apparently
that was not done with this particular executive</text><text start="2995.109" dur="0.891">budget. Was there a reason for that?</text><text start="2996" dur="4.41">We&amp;#39;re still talking to the council, and Dean
will jump in. We&amp;#39;re – you know, the council</text><text start="3000.41" dur="5.49">has done a lot of very impressive work lately
on improving their own process and suggesting</text><text start="3005.9" dur="4.32">some ideas to us about how we can focus better
and on transparency, so we&amp;#39;re going to work</text><text start="3010.22" dur="4.75">with them on that. But there&amp;#39;s more to come
on that as move toward the adopted.</text><text start="3014.97" dur="7">[Reporter] The council had also asked to waive
the fees for universal school lunch. Is that</text><text start="3022.099" dur="0.571">something that is part of this?</text><text start="3022.67" dur="4.61">It&amp;#39;s something I appreciate that they&amp;#39;re advocating
for, and we ultimately want to get to. We&amp;#39;re</text><text start="3027.28" dur="4.41">not there yet for a reason. We have looked
long and hard at the question of what it will</text><text start="3031.69" dur="7">do to our federal funding writ large for school
food, and we are not convinced, at this point,</text><text start="3038.96" dur="3.76">that it won&amp;#39;t unfortunately have the negative
impact of reducing our federal funding substantially.</text><text start="3042.72" dur="5.51">So, we&amp;#39;re continuing to work – Speaker Mark-Viverito
has been very adamant on this point, as has</text><text start="3048.23" dur="5.18">the public advocate, and I appreciate their
depth of feeling. We’re trying to resolve</text><text start="3053.41" dur="3.05">this issue. We can’t yet project if we’re
going to be able to do that in the next few</text><text start="3056.46" dur="5.23">weeks or if it will take more time. But until
we know if there may be a, you know, a net</text><text start="3061.69" dur="2.409">negative in that, we have to be very careful.
Rich?</text><text start="3064.099" dur="5.531">[Reporter] Mr. Mayor, the council also had
proposed1,000 extra or additional police officers.</text><text start="3069.63" dur="5.14">What’s your thinking on that, and what does
this budget say about that?</text><text start="3074.77" dur="5.73">I, again, I know that’s a heartfelt request
on their part, but the fact is, that thank</text><text start="3080.5" dur="5.17">God the NYPD is achieving what it is achieving
with the resources it has now. We’re still</text><text start="3085.67" dur="7">going to be over 34,000, closer to 35,000
cops. Their efforts continue to succeed. We</text><text start="3095.69" dur="3.7">have obviously have beefed up the traffic
enforcement piece, and we think that’s going</text><text start="3099.39" dur="4.5">to have a very big effect. We’re seeing
that already. So we think with the resources</text><text start="3103.89" dur="7">we have, we can keep crime low and continue
to do better in terms of the Vision Zero program.</text><text start="3110.95" dur="4">And as a question of priorities, we think
that it’s right to stay with that amount</text><text start="3114.95" dur="6.84">in terms of policing and focus on some other
priorities that really are hurting right now.</text><text start="3121.79" dur="2.6">Yes?</text><text start="3124.39" dur="7">[Reporter] Speaking of the council, after
they emerged from your budget briefing this</text><text start="3136.47" dur="6.99">morning, they said that the issue of member
items did not come up, and it’s still a</text><text start="3143.46" dur="1.52">question. They say that member items will
be in their budget, that they’re not worried</text><text start="3144.98" dur="1.579">about it. You’ve obviously said many, many
times that you want to get rid of them, especially</text><text start="3146.559" dur="2">given the arrest Ruben Wills yesterday. This—will
member items be in the budget this year?</text><text start="3148.559" dur="2.52">Well look, the Council and I continue to agree
to disagree. We have different perspectives</text><text start="3151.079" dur="5.641">on this. I do think it’s time to end member
items. I think that’s the smart path going</text><text start="3156.72" dur="5.399">forward. But I also respect that the council
has its own prerogatives and, you know, I</text><text start="3162.119" dur="3.831">respect them as the legislative body and we
have to work in partnership. So we’ll continue</text><text start="3165.95" dur="6.45">to work on that issue but, you know, I think
this may be just one of the areas of respectful</text><text start="3172.4" dur="0.6">disagreement.</text><text start="3173" dur="1.809">[Reporter] [inaudible] budget?</text><text start="3174.809" dur="3.191">At this moment, again, there’s a continued
process going on. The council is asserting</text><text start="3178" dur="4.22">their desire to continue it as it is, and
we respect that and we’ll continue to have</text><text start="3182.22" dur="1.129">discussion looking forward to the adopted
budget.</text><text start="3183.349" dur="2.46">[Reporter] It looks – unless I’m misreading
– it looks like you spent the billion out</text><text start="3185.809" dur="7">of the healthcare retiree trust fund. I don’t
see that in here. Maybe it’s a question</text><text start="3193.299" dur="3.891">for Dean. Was that money that was replenished
in February spent?</text><text start="3197.19" dur="6.919">No, we did not touch the retiree health insurance
trust fund. The money that you are referring</text><text start="3204.109" dur="7">to – the billion dollars – is from the
stabilization fund, which has been in existence</text><text start="3211.319" dur="7">for about 25, 30 years. And it is under the
joint control of both the city and the municipal</text><text start="3218.819" dur="3.691">labor council. And that’s one of the things
they had to vote on last week.</text><text start="3222.51" dur="2.95">[Reporter] [inaudible] retiree fund is not
listed here, then?</text><text start="3225.46" dur="1.46">It’s not a change. We had done the –</text><text start="3226.92" dur="1.689">It’s the same as in the preliminary.</text><text start="3228.609" dur="0.25">Exactly.</text><text start="3228.859" dur="0.48">[Reporter] [inaudible]</text><text start="3229.339" dur="1.941">It’s the same as in the preliminary. Yes.</text><text start="3231.28" dur="0.25">Correct.</text><text start="3231.53" dur="4.38">And the point on the stabilization fund is
that that – again, it’s been there for</text><text start="3235.91" dur="4.909">over a quarter century and it’s grown over
time. Its original intention was to address</text><text start="3240.819" dur="5.591">differences in different city health insurance
plans. And over time, there’s been a recognition</text><text start="3246.41" dur="5.61">that this money could be utilized to help
us with our fiscal reality, but there wasn’t</text><text start="3252.02" dur="4.279">a productive relationship between labor and
management in the last few years that might’ve</text><text start="3256.299" dur="5.441">allowed for that. This is really another good
example of how creating a constructive dynamic</text><text start="3261.74" dur="5.77">has allowed us to get some resources into
play that’s helping us with our fiscal health.</text><text start="3267.51" dur="6.069">And this is a really important part of this
larger labor-management cooperation. [Inaudible]</text><text start="3273.579" dur="7">[Reporter] So, Albany obviously didn’t give
you the money that you were asking for for</text><text start="3290.16" dur="1.179">after-school programs. So I was hoping you
could just walk us through exactly how much</text><text start="3291.339" dur="0.941">money and how what you’re allocating now
compares to what you wanted?</text><text start="3292.28" dur="2.819">It’s $145 million. It allows us to go a
substantial amount of the way we wanted to</text><text start="3295.099" dur="6.291">go, but not all the way we wanted to go. Next
year, when after-school-specific funding starts</text><text start="3301.39" dur="5.11">to kick in from Albany, we’ll be able to
do more. But, clearly, the way that the school</text><text start="3306.5" dur="5.089">aid was designated, it indicated specifically
that after-school was an appropriate use and</text><text start="3311.589" dur="3.561">so we’ve devoted that to after-school.</text><text start="3315.15" dur="7">[Reporter] Before the plan was 27,000 seats
would cover 60,000 kids, but it looks like</text><text start="3324.47" dur="0.26">from here you’ve got 34,000 seats covering
100,000 kids. How is that possible?</text><text start="3324.73" dur="4.4">No, no, no. 100,000 is the grand total. There
already was about 60-ish existing in terms</text><text start="3329.13" dur="5.27">of after-school seats for middle school kids.
So it takes us up to about 100,000 total now</text><text start="3334.4" dur="3.689">after-school for middle school kids. And then
there’s also the summer piece where we’ve</text><text start="3338.089" dur="1.691">doubled it with that same funding stream.</text><text start="3339.78" dur="4.98">[Reporter] Does this plan count on a third
tranche of federal funding for Hurricane Sandy</text><text start="3344.76" dur="5.319">relief? And is there any plan to use city
money if that money doesn’t come through</text><text start="3350.079" dur="2">or it’s not what you’re expecting –</text><text start="3352.079" dur="7">I – I will be mindful in my answers. Absolute
total respect to our federal partners. The</text><text start="3360.01" dur="4.89">legislation, of course, was passed to address
the crisis of Sandy in New York State and</text><text start="3364.9" dur="5.3">New Jersey. And we are hopeful that that’s
what will come to pass in the third tranche.</text><text start="3370.2" dur="4.849">Those conversations are continuing. But no,
there is not an assumption of a specific dollar</text><text start="3375.049" dur="2.181">figure in this plan. That’s one of the uncertainties.
Michael?</text><text start="3377.23" dur="7">[Reporter] Mr. Mayor, the police and the fire
unions and other public safety unions as you</text><text start="3386.99" dur="1.559">know are calling for raises that are higher
than what you achieved with the teachers’</text><text start="3388.549" dur="2.81">contract. Is there any wiggle-room in your
budget for that? And what’s your response</text><text start="3391.359" dur="1.611">to folks who say no zeroes for heroes?</text><text start="3392.97" dur="5.389">I’m not a wiggle-room kind of guy. Look,
that’s – there’s going to be constructive</text><text start="3398.359" dur="5.851">conversations with each and every union among
the 151 remaining. And again, the UFT still</text><text start="3404.21" dur="5.95">has to go through its full ratification process.
But the fact that the MLC almost unanimously</text><text start="3410.16" dur="5.389">agreed with the concept of these healthcare
savings – and the fact that one of our very</text><text start="3415.549" dur="6.161">largest unions is well on its way to agreeing
to this particular settlement – clearly</text><text start="3421.71" dur="4.27">indicates – if I’ve ever seen a pattern,
this is a pattern. So there will be individual</text><text start="3425.98" dur="3.66">conversations with each union. There’s a
number of items that are on the table – some</text><text start="3429.64" dur="4.99">economic, some non-economic – in each labor
negotiation. But we feel very confident that</text><text start="3434.63" dur="2.86">this pattern will hold throughout the process.</text><text start="3437.49" dur="1.119">[Reporter] [inaudible]</text><text start="3438.609" dur="4.811">We don’t do lines in the sand either. The
whole concept throughout – and I think you</text><text start="3443.42" dur="6.79">know by now, I don’t negotiate in public.
The reason we were able to achieve we achieved</text><text start="3450.21" dur="5.129">was a respectful relationship – and I want
to tip my cap to Bob Linn again, who really</text><text start="3455.339" dur="3.48">epitomized this – and I can’t tell you
how many labor leaders have told me that,</text><text start="3458.819" dur="5.23">that they appreciated the respectful dynamic
that Bob created the table. We did it discreetly,</text><text start="3464.049" dur="5.471">there was a lot of creativity in the process.
We expect that to continue. So we have a pattern.</text><text start="3469.52" dur="3.539">I believe it’s pretty obvious. We’re going
to work constructively with each union. And</text><text start="3473.059" dur="2.091">I’m confident we’ll get to a good place.</text><text start="3475.15" dur="4.76">[Reporter] One of the economic aspects of
the teacher contract is the money for model</text><text start="3479.91" dur="5.129">teachers and ambassador teachers, etcetera.
Is that money going to be funded based on</text><text start="3485.039" dur="5.491">what you say from the Absent Teacher Reserve
changes? Or is that free and independent,</text><text start="3490.53" dur="1.47">not governed by [inaudible]?</text><text start="3492" dur="2.65">Let’s get Bob Linn to make a cameo here.</text><text start="3494.65" dur="4.76">Commissioner Bob Linn, Office of Labor Relations:
That is not funded out of savings from the</text><text start="3499.41" dur="7">ATR. It’s discretionary at the chancellor
and will be based on economics within the</text><text start="3506.97" dur="0.94">DOE.</text><text start="3507.91" dur="7">[Reporter] I don’t see anything in the after-school
programs about the Priority 7 vouchers. Is</text><text start="3520.78" dur="4.72">that part of this $145 million?</text><text start="3525.5" dur="4.76">The after-school program will, in its own
way, will reach some of the same families,</text><text start="3530.26" dur="4.01">unquestionably. But, you know, as I’ve said,
a lot of the things I want to work on over</text><text start="3534.27" dur="4.74">time, some we could do in this budget, some
will take more time. So I remain committed</text><text start="3539.01" dur="6.12">to resolving some of what I think were the
mistaken policies of the last few years. But</text><text start="3545.13" dur="3.56">that’s going to take some time to achieve
in full. But in this case, some families will</text><text start="3548.69" dur="2.369">certainly benefit from the afterschool funding.
Michael?</text><text start="3551.059" dur="7">[Reporter] Two quick numbers questions. On
page 45, the net cost of the labor settlement</text><text start="3561.03" dur="0.25">from ’14 to ’18, that looks to total about
the $5.5 billion that is allotted to the UFT</text><text start="3561.03" dur="5.309">raises. So I just wondered, do these balance
sheets assume the 10 percent over seven years</text><text start="3566.339" dur="7">for all of the other unions? Or has that not
yet been integrated into these numbers?</text><text start="3578.539" dur="1.471">Can I do a quick tutorial?</text><text start="3580.01" dur="2.559">We would love nothing more.</text><text start="3582.569" dur="5.151">You’ve got 110,000 workers represented by
the UFT. There are another 40,000 workers</text><text start="3587.72" dur="5.369">who are similarly situated with the UFT – the
150,000 employees total who didn’t receive</text><text start="3593.089" dur="3.49">the two fours that the other 200,000 workers
did.</text><text start="3596.579" dur="5.371">In 2008 and 2009. So I’m going to add to
that tutorial – 150,000 in 2008/2009 did</text><text start="3601.95" dur="6.159">not get the same increases the other 200,000
city workers got. Ergo, it was only a matter</text><text start="3608.109" dur="2.341">of time before someday that was going to get
addressed.</text><text start="3610.45" dur="7">If you take the full 350,000 workers, and
you assume a nine-year settlement for those</text><text start="3617.66" dur="7">that didn’t participate in the ‘08/’09
round, and you assume everybody – all 350,000</text><text start="3625.289" dur="5.75">– get the same 10 percent over seven years
going forward, the total cost of that is the</text><text start="3631.039" dur="7">$13.4 billion total, which is offset by $3.4
billion in health savings, $1 billion from</text><text start="3639.17" dur="6.53">the stabilization fund, $3.5 billion from
the labor reserve, and that is the net of</text><text start="3645.7" dur="5.589">$3.5 billion – $5.5 billion, excuse me – $5.5
billion net that covers all workers for the</text><text start="3651.289" dur="2.55">entire pattern.</text><text start="3653.839" dur="6.181">I hasten to add, there is an additional briefing
– a technical briefing – here after. So</text><text start="3660.02" dur="2.7">feel free to ask more, but I’m saying a
lot of the detailed questions you can also</text><text start="3662.72" dur="1.68">treat in that technical briefing.</text><text start="3664.4" dur="7">[Reporter] Mr. Mayor, what made you change
your mind [inaudible] more money into the</text><text start="3675.39" dur="3.78">budget for road resurfacing? And I’m curious
as to how you pay for it? I know it’s a</text><text start="3679.17" dur="0.379">capital expense, but are you going to have
to borrow more money to pay for it or are</text><text start="3679.549" dur="0.25">you –</text><text start="3679.569" dur="3.99">No, no. I really want to – I really want
to set the record straight that we did not</text><text start="3683.559" dur="5.661">change our minds. In the preliminary, we continued
the November plan of the previous administration</text><text start="3689.22" dur="5.339">on the capital side until we could come to
a series of decisions. So certain individuals</text><text start="3694.559" dur="4.821">out there suggested that we had bought into
the notion of less repaving. That was never</text><text start="3699.38" dur="4.79">true and we tried to clarify it. Unfortunately,
the clarification wasn’t heard. The preliminary</text><text start="3704.17" dur="6">budget accepted the previous administration’s
capital plan, put it in a holding pattern,</text><text start="3710.17" dur="4.97">and we said explicitly – come May, you’re
going to see our capital plan start to emerge.</text><text start="3715.14" dur="4.33">When we looked at it, we said, clearly we
needed more resources for repaving. This is</text><text start="3719.47" dur="4.329">the number that gets us to 1,000 lane miles
being repaved in Fiscal ’15.</text><text start="3723.799" dur="7">[Reporter] [inaudible] pay for it? Is it just
that you’re reprioritizing from the capital</text><text start="3731.529" dur="0.25">plan or do you need to borrow –</text><text start="3731.619" dur="1.92">It’s part of the capital budget that the
mayor outlined. It’s not different.</text><text start="3733.539" dur="4.381">[Reporter] In order to pay for it, what do
you have to, are you –</text><text start="3737.92" dur="4.3">Once again, two different – there are increases
in the capital plan. That&amp;#39;s certainly reflective</text><text start="3742.22" dur="5.74">of that. There&amp;#39;s also a stretching out over
the capital plan, so yes. There are increases</text><text start="3747.96" dur="4.74">in the capital plan, and that service was
the slide the mayor showed you, where the</text><text start="3752.7" dur="6.03">historical average, with city revenues, is
below 15 percent.</text><text start="3758.73" dur="4.139">[Reporter] -- that I don&amp;#39;t understand. I know
that you have to keep –</text><text start="3762.869" dur="1.17">We are borrowing for that money, yes.</text><text start="3764.039" dur="7">[Reporter] Is that level below the historical
15 percent, [inaudible] number of taxes you</text><text start="3774.089" dur="0.25">collected increases, you could also increase
the –</text><text start="3774.089" dur="0.25">The number of what increases?</text><text start="3774.19" dur="0.29">[Reporter] Because tax collections increased,
you can always increase the amount of money</text><text start="3774.48" dur="7">you borrow because it&amp;#39;s a percentage of the
tax increase –</text><text start="3783.119" dur="0.73">Let me start and then –</text><text start="3783.849" dur="4.381">[Reporter] Are you increasing your borrowing,
or are you just reprioritizing the capital</text><text start="3788.23" dur="1.01">plan, or both?</text><text start="3789.24" dur="5.46">Let me try, and Dean will jump in. The – because
I think a really important thing to clarify,</text><text start="3794.7" dur="3.829">and I learned this along the way, many times,
many ways, particularly in the council. There&amp;#39;s</text><text start="3798.529" dur="4.121">a lot of confusion out in the world. All the
people that we represent, we have to explain</text><text start="3802.65" dur="3.84">this to, between expense budget and capital
budget. So obviously, expense budget based</text><text start="3806.49" dur="5.65">on, you know, hard revenue, with a real finite
limit because of that. Capital budget, you</text><text start="3812.14" dur="3.659">have an option of how much to borrow, up to
a realistic point, and that is – one of</text><text start="3815.799" dur="4.27">the obvious indicators is how much debt service
you have to do. Dean said – a couple of</text><text start="3820.069" dur="4.381">things. One, we thought that the capital assumptions
of the November plan were faulty in terms</text><text start="3824.45" dur="3.72">of how, when, money would spent, how it would
be spent. We made a number of changes based</text><text start="3828.17" dur="4.34">on that. We saw some things that we knew couldn&amp;#39;t
possibly be done in the time frame indicated.</text><text start="3832.51" dur="4.339">We, in some cases, replaced them with other
things we thought were realistic, or we changed</text><text start="3836.849" dur="3.46">the timelines on them, et cetera. We also
determined what we thought was a fair amount</text><text start="3840.309" dur="4.141">of borrowing, to allow us to achieve the things
we had to achieve. We were convinced that</text><text start="3844.45" dur="3.159">we had serious infrastructure issues that
had to be addressed. We were convinced we</text><text start="3847.609" dur="5.21">had to do better by our school system. Obviously,
had to fund the affordable housing plan. So,</text><text start="3852.819" dur="4.621">we figured, through that, what would be a
fair amount for the capital budget overall,</text><text start="3857.44" dur="3.859">and that&amp;#39;s what we locked in. But it was very
important to us that the debt service not</text><text start="3861.299" dur="3.711">increase too much, because that does affect
your expense budget.</text><text start="3865.01" dur="0.49">[Inaudible]</text><text start="3865.5" dur="2.22">Are we what?</text><text start="3867.72" dur="3.54">[Reporter] -- the amount of money you are
borrowing?</text><text start="3871.26" dur="1.529">Absolutely. Absolutely. From where to where?</text><text start="3872.789" dur="5.371">So, in city funds, it&amp;#39;s about $3.2 billion,
because there&amp;#39;s obviously an aggressive housing</text><text start="3878.16" dur="6.74">plan. There are increases in education, and
there are some increases in DOT. Those are</text><text start="3884.9" dur="0.56">the major ones.</text><text start="3885.46" dur="0.73">Over four years.</text><text start="3886.19" dur="0.99">Over the four-year period.</text><text start="3887.18" dur="1.679">Right, $3.2 billion over the four years.</text><text start="3888.859" dur="6.551">[Reporter] My initial question – the decision
to increase money for roads – you made that</text><text start="3895.41" dur="0.649">decision because…?</text><text start="3896.059" dur="5.28">Because we got a DOT commissioner who looked
at the situation, looked at the preliminary</text><text start="3901.339" dur="3.541">– looked at the budget that was handed to
us in November and assessed what we could</text><text start="3904.88" dur="3.88">get done, and she came to the conclusion that
we needed to get to 1,000 lane miles, and</text><text start="3908.76" dur="3.829">this is what we would cost – what it would
cost, and we thought that was a priority.</text><text start="3912.589" dur="0.49">Henry?</text><text start="3913.079" dur="2.181">Oh, I’m sorry, Dean wants to clarify.</text><text start="3915.26" dur="6.19">So what I gave you were the capital commitment
numbers, not the increase in borrowing, alright?</text><text start="3921.45" dur="5.629">So I will give you the actual debt – that
was the commitment in the capital plan over</text><text start="3927.079" dur="6.311">the four years, the cumulative number on the
capital plan for city funding. What I’ll</text><text start="3933.39" dur="4.56">give you after this is the exact increase
in debt service, what we were modeling—</text><text start="3937.95" dur="1.389">Reporter: [Inaudible] capital spending [inaudible]
–</text><text start="3939.339" dur="4.74">Budget Director Dean Fuleihan: It’s the
increase in the capital commitments, and the</text><text start="3944.079" dur="3.141">capital commitments are funded through our
debt service.</text><text start="3947.22" dur="3.05">Okay, let’s—and we can do more in the
technical briefing. More – let’s keep</text><text start="3950.27" dur="1.049">going guys. Henry, did you have something?</text><text start="3951.319" dur="7">[Reporter] I do. The years through 2020 in
which you are paying the back pay, how much</text><text start="3961.77" dur="2.309">is that going to cost?</text><text start="3964.079" dur="5.581">So that’s Fiscal ’19 – help me out ¬– Fiscal
’20, and Fiscal ’21. And I’m going to</text><text start="3969.66" dur="0.369">start before –</text><text start="3970.029" dur="2.611">Reporter: [Inaudible] those are calendar years?</text><text start="3972.64" dur="5.1">No, fiscals. Fiscal. Work with me. Work with
me. The labor settlement goes through Fiscal</text><text start="3977.74" dur="5.98">’18. I’m looking at my panel of judges.
The restructured payments take you to Fiscal</text><text start="3983.72" dur="6.41">’19, Fiscal ’20, Fiscal ’21. Key point,
the healthcare savings initiated through this</text><text start="3990.13" dur="5.5">agreement, ratified almost unanimously by
the MLC, are going to continue to be a part</text><text start="3995.63" dur="4.02">of the life of this city and the city government
going forward, so yes there’s some payments</text><text start="3999.65" dur="5.409">we have to do to finish the old business.
And this I really want to emphasize. Again,</text><text start="4005.059" dur="4.831">we were left with an unprecedented dynamic,
and with 150,000 workers who didn’t get</text><text start="4009.89" dur="4.729">treated like the other 200,000. That was going
to have to be resolved someday. It should</text><text start="4014.619" dur="3.821">have been resolved in the past administration.
It really should have, by any normal measure.</text><text start="4018.44" dur="5.05">We’re resolving it now. The good news is
there’s also a pattern now being set, a</text><text start="4023.49" dur="4.849">reality being set of healthcare savings that
we think will not only live, but will grows</text><text start="4028.339" dur="2.77">deeper over time.</text><text start="4031.109" dur="1.851">[Inaudible]</text><text start="4032.96" dur="7">It’s going to cost $4.3 of $5 billion, is
that total for the lump-sums. There will be</text><text start="4042.41" dur="6.1">an additional $1.9 billion of healthcare savings,
so that leaves about $2.4 billion of costs.</text><text start="4048.51" dur="7">Let me explain. The 200,000 workers who received
the increases before are not part of this.</text><text start="4056.329" dur="6.121">The lump-sum restructuring payments are only
for the 150,000 who didn’t receive the same</text><text start="4062.45" dur="7">increases that the 200,000 already have been
enjoying since 2008 and 2009. Those payments</text><text start="4070.589" dur="7">of that restructured lump-sums, they will
be made in five pieces – One in ’15, one</text><text start="4077.799" dur="4.351">in ’17, and then the three payments that
we talked about before, which add up to, for</text><text start="4082.15" dur="6.07">all 150,000 workers, the $4.3-5 billion with
the continued healthcare savings. They end</text><text start="4088.22" dur="5.53">at that point. So this is not a situation
of increases that go on forever or increase</text><text start="4093.75" dur="3.109">in time. They are gone after Fiscal ’21.</text><text start="4096.859" dur="5.46">And one more rejoinder on that. The whole
goal here was to create normalcy, and lasting</text><text start="4102.319" dur="7">normalcy. It&amp;#39;s really important for my eventual
successor to receive a situation where labor</text><text start="4110.089" dur="4.141">contracts are up to date, where they&amp;#39;re not
dealing with past burdens, and we can move</text><text start="4114.23" dur="5.96">forward in a fiscally stable environment.
So, as challenging as this was, due to Bob&amp;#39;s</text><text start="4120.19" dur="3.92">efforts, and a lot of cooperation with our
partners in municipal labor – this clears</text><text start="4124.11" dur="5.3">the decks once and for all. And we now are
in a position to have consistent labor contracts</text><text start="4129.41" dur="0.74">from this point on. Kate?</text><text start="4130.15" dur="1.75">[Reporter] Can you tell us precisely what
amount of health care savings you accounted</text><text start="4131.9" dur="6.7">for and factored in for each of the four years
[Inaudible] financial plan? And at what point</text><text start="4138.6" dur="7">would you decide that it&amp;#39;s, that they&amp;#39;re not
being realized? How soon would you make that</text><text start="4150.27" dur="0.25">call?</text><text start="4150.31" dur="6.21">Ok, we, let&amp;#39;s be – I&amp;#39;m going to start. These
savings will happen, period. They are guaranteed.</text><text start="4156.52" dur="4.98">What&amp;#39;s clear is, there is a menu of ways to
get there, but there is an arbitrator process</text><text start="4161.5" dur="1.69">that guarantees the outcome.</text><text start="4163.19" dur="2.41">[Reporter] -- what point would that kick in?</text><text start="4165.6" dur="5.46">Commissioner Linn: So we have obligations,
agreements, to reach $400 million dollars</text><text start="4171.06" dur="7">of savings in Fiscal &amp;#39;15, $700 million in
Fiscal &amp;#39;16, a billion in &amp;#39;17, and $1.3 billion</text><text start="4178.81" dur="5.65">in &amp;#39;18, and those are recurring savings, so
it&amp;#39;s not just for that year. Those $1.3 billion</text><text start="4184.46" dur="6.5">recurs and increases in the future based on
healthcare cost increases. We will, each year,</text><text start="4190.96" dur="4.62">analyze whether or not we&amp;#39;ve received the
targeted amount that we&amp;#39;ve agreed to. And</text><text start="4195.58" dur="3.61">if not, we will immediately – we have the
right to go to the arbitrator for interim</text><text start="4199.19" dur="5.06">relief. So that each year we will monitor
it, and we will measure it, and if we don&amp;#39;t</text><text start="4204.25" dur="4.15">make those savings, we will get additional
relief.</text><text start="4208.4" dur="3.97">Last call. Last call. Rich?</text><text start="4212.37" dur="2.41">[Reporter] Mr. Mayor, did you ever expect
to have to deal with all of these numbers,</text><text start="4214.78" dur="6.6">and do you consider yourself a numbers guy,
or were you – did you try to stay away from</text><text start="4221.38" dur="1.71">accounting and things like that?</text><text start="4223.09" dur="7">I emphatically tried to stay away from accounting.
I think I am traditional in this sense. I</text><text start="4230.84" dur="6.31">didn&amp;#39;t seek to learn about this field in my
spare time. But I put it through the prism,</text><text start="4237.15" dur="3.05">and I don&amp;#39;t want to sound hackneyed, but I
think it&amp;#39;s true, I put it through the prism</text><text start="4240.2" dur="4.2">of, you know, someone sitting around a kitchen
table balancing their household budget. And</text><text start="4244.4" dur="5.17">I&amp;#39;ve got to tell you, it becomes real clear
real quick, when you look at the reality of</text><text start="4249.57" dur="7">this city, how careful you have to be. This
is a cautious document on purpose. We see</text><text start="4258.14" dur="4.86">what happened in recent years, we see some
of the threats, and we know we have to be</text><text start="4263" dur="5.87">in a careful stance to protect against future
disruptions, so we can keep moving the pieces</text><text start="4268.87" dur="4.87">we have to move. I also – I haven&amp;#39;t always
articulated it so perfectly in the past, but</text><text start="4273.74" dur="5.54">again, I am a traditionalist in the sense
of, I dislike things like a labor contract</text><text start="4279.28" dur="5.84">hanging out there, creating uncertainty. It
just – that always rubbed me the wrong way.</text><text start="4285.12" dur="3.95">And I said to my colleagues, you know, let&amp;#39;s
do everything we know how to do to get this</text><text start="4289.07" dur="4.56">done as quickly as possible. They surpassed
my every expectation in the speed with which</text><text start="4293.63" dur="5.1">they achieved it. But I think you have to
have certainty. The lack of certainty really</text><text start="4298.73" dur="4.79">bothered me. And the one thing that I&amp;#39;m really,
deeply appreciative about, about the way we&amp;#39;ve</text><text start="4303.52" dur="6.3">gotten to this point is – this is something
that now, you know, we can bank on for the</text><text start="4309.82" dur="4.76">remainder of our time in office in this term,
and we hope that, you know, in the future,</text><text start="4314.58" dur="4.94">whoever is in office can bank on it as well.
And it gives us a really strong foundation</text><text start="4319.52" dur="1.85">for the future of this city. Thanks everyone.</text></transcript>